{"test_questions": [[{"question": "A(n) __________ is an excised piece of leaf or stem tissue used in micropropagation.", "opta": "microshoot", "optb": "medium", "optc": "explant", "optd": "scion", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Protoplasts can be produced from suspension cultures, callus tissues or intact tissues by enzymatic treatment with", "opta": "cellulotyic enzymes", "optb": "pectolytic enzymes", "optc": "both cellulotyic and pectolytic enzymes", "optd": "proteolytic enzymes", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is considered as the disadvantage of conventional plant tissue culture for clonal propagation?", "opta": "Multiplication of sexually derived sterile hybrids", "optb": "Less multiplication of disease free plants", "optc": "Storage and transportation of propogates", "optd": "Both (b) and (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is meant by 'Organ culture' ?", "opta": "Maintenance alive of a whole organ, after removal from the organism by partial immersion in a nutrient fluid", "optb": "Introduction of a new organ in an animal body with a view to create genetic mutation in the progenies of that animal", "optc": "Cultivation of organs in a laboratory through the synthesis of tissues", "optd": "The aspects of culture in community which are mainly dedicated by the need of a specified organ of the human body", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which method of plant propagation involves the use of girdling?", "opta": "Grafting", "optb": "Cuttings", "optc": "Layering", "optd": "Micropropagation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Organogenesis is", "opta": "formation of callus tissue", "optb": "formation of root and shoots on callus tissue", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "genesis of organs", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is used in the culture of regenerating protoplasts, single cells or very dilute cell suspensions?", "opta": "Nurse medium", "optb": "Nurse or feeder culture", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a callus culture", "opta": "increasing level of cytokinin to a callus induces shoot formation and increasing level of auxin promote root formation", "optb": "increasing level of auxin to a callus induces shoot formation and increasing level of cytokinin promote root formation", "optc": "auxins and cytokinins are not required", "optd": "only auxin is required for root and shoot formation", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Protoplasts are the cells devoid of", "opta": "cell membrane", "optb": "cell wall", "optc": "both cell wall and cell membrane", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which breeding method uses a chemical to strip the cell wall of plant cells of two sexually incompatible species?", "opta": "Mass selection", "optb": "Protoplast fusion", "optc": "Transformation", "optd": "Transpiration", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The phenomenon of the reversion of mature cells to the meristematic state leading to the formation of callus is known as", "opta": "redifferentiation", "optb": "dedifferentiation", "optc": "either (a) or (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cell fusion method includes the preparation of large number of", "opta": "plant cells stripped of their cell wall", "optb": "single plant cell stripped of their cell wall", "optc": "plant cells with cell wall", "optd": "cells from different species", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Subculturing is similar to propagation by cuttings because", "opta": "it separates multiple microshoots and places them in a medium", "optb": "it uses scions to produce new microshoots", "optc": "they both use in vitro growing conditions", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ability of the component cells of callus to form a whole plant is known as", "opta": "redifferentiation", "optb": "dedifferentiation", "optc": "either (a) or (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is/are the benefit(s) of micropropagation or clonal propagation?", "opta": "Rapid multiplication of superior clones", "optb": "Multiplication of disease free plants", "optc": "Multiplication of sexually derived sterile hybrids", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When plated only in nutrient medium, how much time is required for the protoplast to synthesize new cell wall?", "opta": "2-5 days", "optb": "5-10 days", "optc": "10-15 days", "optd": "15-17 days", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cellular totipotency is the property of", "opta": "plants", "optb": "animals", "optc": "bacteria", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Agrobacterium based gene transfer is efficient", "opta": "only with dicots", "optb": "only with monocots", "optc": "with both monocots and dicots", "optd": "with majority monocots and few dicots", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}